Okay. So, we've talked about factors in the
Ok我们已经抽象地讨论过因子
abstract and in your head you're thinking, "Okay,
你可能会这么想：
it's a vector where the values for each stock are
“因子是一个向量
proportional to some aspect of the future performance of that stock."
每支股票的向量值与该股票未来业绩成一定的比例”
Yes, you're right.
你想对了
When I first learned this,
当我第一次知道这些时
in some ways, it wasn't very satisfying to me.
对这种结果不是太满意
But there's a sense in which that's what you need to know.
从某种程度上来说需要这么理解
But I want to give you more because there is more to
但是还有更多含义
the story but that's where it gets more complicated.
这时候会变得复杂起来
So stay with me and I promise it will pay
请认真聆听
dividends in your learning for the next several lessons.
你肯定会在接下来的几节课用到这些知识的
There is a formalism behind factors,
因子遵守某种形式
let me tell you a little about it.
下面我解释下
There's such a thing in the statistical literature called a factor model.
统计学领域有个概念 叫做因子模型
A factor model is a statistical model used to
因子模型是一种统计学模型
describe variability among observed correlated variables,
它通过潜在更少的未观察到变量（称为因子）
in terms of potentially smaller number of unobserved variables called factors.
描述观察到的相关变量之间的变化性
This method is actually used in several disciplines including biology,
多个学科都用到了这种方法
psychology, and business, as well as finance.
包括生物 心理 商业和财经领域
Whenever practitioners are looking to discover a smaller number of
当我们想要挖掘更少的潜在变量
so-called latent variables that explain correlations in a set of variables of interest.
来解释一组目标变量之间的关系时
We could apply this type of analysis to many situations,
我们就可以应用这种分析方法
but in finance, we're typically interested in modelling the returns of several assets.
在金融领域 我们通常想要对多个资产的收益率建模
We might notice that the returns of some assets seem to vary together.
我们可能发现某些资产的收益率会共同变化
Are these companies similar in some way such that some
是这些公司有相似之处
underlying effect influences both of them in the same way?
某个变化对它们的影响方式一样吗？
What if we could model the returns of a large group of stocks with
如果我们能用少量变量对大量股票的收益率进行建模 效果会怎样？
a smaller set of variables which explain their common variability?
这些变量能够解释股票的共同变化
This is what we attempt to do with factor models.
我们就是希望用因子模型做到这一点
The observed variables, in our case returns,
观察到的变量（收益率）
are modeled as linear combinations of the factors returns plus error terms.
用因子收益率和误差项的线性组合进行建模
So a generic linear factor model looks something like
一般的线性因子模型是这样的
this: we model the return on a stock,
我们将股票 债券
bond mutual fund or something else as
共同基金等的收益率建模为
a linear function of returns attributed to several factors.
多个因子的收益率的线性函数
The values of these factor returns are the same for all stocks.
这些因子收益率的值对于所有股票来说是一样的
The factor exposures tell you how much the return of
因子暴露度表示每单位的因子收益率变化
an individual asset should change per unit change in a factor return.
会导致单个资产收益率变化多少
Here, the last term, the error term,
最后的误差项表示
is the portion of the return on asset not related to any of the factors.
资产收益率中与任何因子无关的部分
In words, the return of any stock, i,
也就是说 任何股票 i 的收益率
can be decomposed into the returns of
可以分解为因子的收益率
factors times the stock's exposures to those factors,
乘以股票相对于这些因子的暴露度
plus an unexplained portion.
加上无法解释的部分